你促成了巴蒂塔斯家那个女人的买卖
You brokered the sale of a woman from the house of Batiatus.
肩膀后面有主人家的标记
The mark of the domina upon the back of her shoulder.
她在哪里
Where is she?
我们会找到她的 兄弟
We will find her, brother,
凡是阻止你们重逢的人 格杀勿论
and see everyone that has kept her from your arms to the afterlife.
罗马人当我们是狗 就要他们付出血的代价
We will see the Romans bleed for taking us as dogs.
斯巴达克斯是我们共同的敌人
Spartacus is enemy to us both.
那家伙从你眼皮底下溜走多少次了
The man takes habit of slipping through your fingers,
你究竟哪儿来的信心
what moves you to certainty of victory?
因为这是诸神的意愿
Because the gods themselves will it.
愿诸神保佑你
May the gods bless you.
对于失去荣誉的野兽来说只有一个地方可去
There is but one place for an animal without honor.
是你
You.
我是带着礼物来的
I come bearing a gift.
这礼物能助你铲除斯巴达克斯
It should set you upon path to the fall of spartacus.
《斯巴达克斯：复仇》
《多数》
闭上你们的臭嘴
Quiet your fucking bleating!
你冷静点
Still yourself.
就这样也能到矿上做工
This how you came for the mine?
你们这群听不懂人话的东西
By not heeding fucking command?
自己解开锁链
See yourselves free.
你喜欢出其不意啊
You favor clever strategy.
攻敌人的后门
Fuck the man from behind.
今儿开了个好头
A good start to the day.
而且只会越来越好
I would see it built upon…
我要找一个叫妮维雅的女人
I seek a woman named Naevia.
在巴蒂塔斯家灭门之前被赶了出去
She was cast out from the House of Batiatus before its fall.
巴蒂塔斯家
Batiatus?
你是斯巴达克斯吗
You are Spartacus?!
我是克雷斯
I am Crixus.
我旁边那个傻子才是斯巴达克斯
Spartacus stands the fool beside me.
他要找的这个女人美若天仙
The woman he seeks is of rare beauty.
背后有她主人家的标记
The mark of her domina upon her back.
她被人从…
She was carried from…
斯巴达克斯说剑终有一天能变轻
Spartacus tells a sword becomes lighter in time.
杀人从来不是轻巧的事
It is a heavy thing, to rob a man of life.
不过杀罗马人就另当别论
Less so that of a Roman shit.
别走远了
Stay close by.
我去帮忙搬东西 这样才好…
I will help shoulder weight until we can
那个姑娘
The girl…
妮维雅
Naevia…
我知道
Her fate…
她的下落
known to me…
那就快说
Speak it then.
给我一匹马 放我一条生路
Spare a horse, and my life.
快说
Speak.
虽然人手多了
They add to our number.
却帮不了我的忙
Yet not my cause.
我们会找到她的
We will find her.
你这句话不知道说了多少遍
Words you have spoken many times
诸神就是不作理会
yet still ignored by the gods.
那人提到了你的女人
The man, he spoke of your woman.
他说了什么
What did he say?
快说啊
Find fucking voice!
她死了
Dead.
妮维雅死了
Naevia is dead.
真不敢相信她已经走了
I cannot believe she is gone.
诸神又一次忽略了最需要他们庇佑的人
The gods again turn from those most worthy of blessing.
虽然我对他没什么好感
I hold no love for the man.
看到他如此伤心 我心里也不好受
Yet it tears heart, to see him so.
她是怎么死的
How did she meet her end?
巴蒂塔斯把她利用完了
Naevia was put to cart for Lucania
就扔进了去往卢卡尼亚的马车
having served purpose for Batiatus' ambition.
她死在矿上了
She perished in the mines?
她受到了折磨
She gave life in passage,
在路上由于伤势过重而死
from injuries borne of mistreatment.
死了反而是好事
Death a kindness then,
不用再承受这样的命运
to be spared such a fate.
获得解脱的只有死者
Kindness only to the one taken.
他还是一句话不说
The man yet stands mute.
这就是你送来讨好我的礼物吗
This is what you would offer me to gain favor?
一尊流血的雕塑
A statue that bleeds?
奥诺玛默斯自认为是极重荣誉的人
Oenomaus believes himself a man of honor.
肉体的痛苦不足以让他出卖弟兄
Pain alone will not move him to betray his brothers.
我非常了解他
and I know the man well.
把他交到我手上
Given over to my hands
别以为我不记得
Oh do not think I've forgotten
你都有什么手段 奴隶
what your hands are capable of, slave.
要不是你帮助巴蒂塔斯
Or how they aided Batiatus
我也不用收拾这个烂摊子
in tethering me to this house.
我只是按照主人的命令办事
I but did as my dominus commanded,
不作别的考虑
absent thought of refusal.
如今我同样忠心耿耿为您办事
As I would faithfully serve you now,
势必要斯巴达克斯伏法
in seeing Spartacus brought to his end.
你嘴上说的好听
You speak of loyalties.
却还留着巴蒂塔斯家的标记
Yet the mark of Batiatus brings allegiance to question.
肉体的疤痕而已
A blight upon flesh.
却总是让人怀疑我的企图
Forever mocking more noble intentions.
证明给我看
Prove them.
我就留你一命 看看你究竟有没有用
And live to see if you are of further use.
如您所愿
Your will.
这就动手
My hands.
你要有耐心
You must be patient.
诸神把奥诺玛默斯送上门来
The gods would not deliver Oenomaus,
肯定是有原因的
only to mock us with his silence.
我不光怀疑诸神的旨意
The sum of my doubt does not lie with the gods alone.
还怀疑帮他们传达旨意的人
It's equally shared with their messenger.
你总算露面了
Ah. Here is our man.
你还真是有心 终于想到我们了
Courteous to finally acknowledge our presence.
非常抱歉 我不知道你们来了
Apologies. I was unaware of your arrival.
都是我的错
The fault is mine.
我见到父亲太高兴
Between happy reunion with father
又忙着跟瓦里留斯打听罗马的消息
and plying Varinius for news of Rome…
这是角斗士训练师的妻子吧
Is this the lanista's wife?
街头巷尾都在议论的幸运之人
The one they whisper of in the streets?
露迪雅
Lucretia.
看到你还活着
To find you alive.
真是奥林匹斯诸神的保佑
It's a blessing from Olympus.
我只是听从诸神的安排
I am but its humble instrument.
你太谦虚了
You are overly modest.
能从那种恐怖浩劫中生还
To have survived such horrors…
肯定是朱庇特明白你的价值所在
Jupiter himself must have taken note of your worth.
瓦里留斯是来主持比赛的
Varinius comes to present games.
比赛
Games?
为期两周的血腥盛宴
Two weeks of blood and sport!
消除斯巴达克斯的阴影 虽说他尚未伏法
To move the city from heavy thought of Spartacus, yet untamed.
如果你的手下能出阵
It shall be glorious spectacle…
开幕庆典就相当壮观了
made more so by your men presented in opening celebration.
威武的士兵外加贵宾席的露迪雅
The sight of them coupled with Lucretia in the pulvinus
无疑能够安抚民众
shall help calm the citizenry.
我感到非常荣幸
An honor, I would happily oblige,
不过他们正在南方忙着剿匪呢
were they not otherwise occupied in the south.
那有什么突破性进展吗
Do they draw any closer to their goal?
或是斯巴达克斯又溜不见了
Or does Spartacus yet elude them,
如同上次在集市时一样
as I heard he did in the market?
或许赛普修斯的手下可以出席你的比赛
Perhaps Seppius' men could march in your games.
众所周知你对他们的影响力很大
It's well known you hold considerable sway with them.
赛普修斯的手下跟你的不同 不是正规军
Seppius' men do not carry the seal of Rome, as your men do.
给瓦里留斯上好酒
Show good Varinius to wine,
再去观赏城市的迷人风光
and enticing view of the city below.
乐意之极
I would voice no argument.
那走吧
Come then.
我保证好好地招待你
I shall see you properly attended.
瓦里留斯在元老院备受尊重
Varinius is admired within the Senate.
这一点你要注意了
A thing to be carefully considered
等到流言蜚语满天飞就来不及了
before words fly from errant fucking tongue.
我和他难道不是平起平坐吗
Do I not stand his equal?
头衔相同罢了
In title only.
他们认为你是没能力的孩子
They think you an incompetent child,
连自己的屁股都擦不干净
unable to wipe clean his own shit.
所以对同级的民政官表现得尊重一点
So a show of respect towards a fellow praetor
从而平息他人的质疑 不失为明智的选择
would be wise step towards quieting doubt. Hmm?
不光是在元老院里
Not only among the Senate.
卡普亚在北边
Capua, to the north.
我们现在在这里
Our current position, here.
往东走 到维苏威
To the east, Vesuvius.
安营扎寨的绝佳地点
Strong position to make camp.
往南能打庞贝
Within striking distance of Pompeii to the south.
或者往西北打那不勒斯
Or Neapolis to the northwest.
战俘都在这里的港口下船
Prison ships often empty at its ports.
然后被变卖为奴
Vomiting men to be sold into slavery.
我们兄弟俩就是这样 那是很久以前了
As my brother and I were, a lifetime ago.
我是从亚得里亚海
I was carried across the Adriatic,
再到东部海岸的
to the eastern seaboard.
我对那不勒斯了解不多
I know little of Neapolis.
带到海岸的都是战士吗
There are fighting men, brought to its shores?
他们是战俘
Captured in foreign wars.
天生就是罗马的敌人
Already enemies of Rome,
很容易招到我们这边来
easily recruited to our cause.
非常合理 想法很好
A reasonable course, well thought.
我去告诉克雷斯
I shall break words with Crixus.
告诉他干嘛
Towards what end?
他代表高卢人
He stands for the Gauls.
他们全都是垃圾
Then he is waist deep in shit.
他们占到我们的半数 而且
They are half our number, and much needed
去那不勒斯肯定大有用处
in any attempt on Neapolis.
他本人也需要从悲伤中走出来
The man himself is in need of distraction from wounded soul.
你是怎么挺过来的
How did you survive?
当你永远失去了心爱的女人
After your woman was taken from you forever?
谁说我挺过来了
The man that I was did not.
我不过是行尸走肉
I am but bones and flesh,
没有了跳动的心
void of beating heart.
我们会用罗马人的鲜血
We will see empty chest filled.
填满你空虚的内心
With the blood of Romans.
血海汪洋也洗不尽我所铸成的大错
An ocean of it would not wash away what I have done.
你做错什么了
What you have done?
我一心得到妮维雅的爱
I pursued Naevia's affections,
完全忽视了暴露的危险
regardless of concern towards discovery.
没想过如果暴露了
Of what Lucretia would do if…
露迪雅的报复
betrayal were known.
妮维雅因为我的一己私欲
Naevia is gone from this world
离开了人世
because of my selfish desires.
爱不是我们选择的
We do not choose love.
该来的时候自会到来
It claims each man as it will.
令人无法自拔 直到生不如死
And it grips until there is nothing left.
空手握起就是拳头
An empty hand can yet become a fist.
像妮维雅那样受到束缚的奴隶有多少
How many more remain shackled in servitude, as Naevia was?
没有爱的希望和温存的爱抚
Without hope of love or gentle touch?
只要我们齐心合力打破枷锁
Together we can strike chain from neck
我早就听说过你的这种想法了
On this subject I have heard your thoughts.
让我静一静
Leave me to my own.
她曾经充满了活力
She was a radiant spirit.
却身为奴隶而死
Yet she died a slave.
我的妻子也是一样
A fate shared by my wife.
我不愿意看到他们这样的人死去
I would not see more like them fall.
而明明可以扭转乾坤的人袖手旁观
Because men who could make difference stood idle.
往他心口捅一刀都比他现在好受
A sword in his chest would be a blow less felt.
我们都做出了各自的牺牲
We have all made sacrifices.
现在轮到克雷斯了
Crixus now makes his.
我要告诉他真相
I would speak with him…
你的话只能带来更可怕的后果
Your words would only cause greater suffering.
如果他知道真相
If he knew the truth…
我不希望你和那些人一起白白送死
I would not have you and countless others fall in vain attempt.
过来
Come.
去那不勒斯的计划还有很多细节没有商量
There is much planning yet needed towards Neapolis.
啊 空虚的目光
Oh, that vacant gaze.
我以前见过你这种眼神
I've witnessed it before.
是你在地下角斗场等待死神降临的时候
When you were upon your knees in the Pits, awaiting death.
还是你在渴望死神降临呢
Or were you longing for it?
所以你才选择在那样的地方
Is that why you sought out a place
毫无荣耀的地方出现
void of precious honor?
想把强大的奥诺玛默斯
A thought drags the mighty Oenomaus
带到冥界的深处
into the depths of the underworld?
在那里 你对这个家族的背叛
Your betrayal of the house that saved you
可以免受折磨
from such torment there?
兄弟之盟让你从教练变成了
A brotherhood turning your instruction as Doctore
叛徒和凶手
to treachery or murder?
还是阿舒尔从你手下捡回一命
Or that Ashur escaped your attempt to rob him of life?
这都不重要
A thing of low importance.
我们大可既往不咎
Let us set past behind us,
展望未来 不必为此伤和气
and turn eye towards less quarrelsome future.
不行啊
Ah, No no!
你要开口求我
You must ask for it.
你必须打破沉默 开口说话
You must break silence and speak.
你想喝水吗
You thirst for water?
想活下去吗
For the release of death?
说出来 就满足你的愿望
Free your tongue, and see desires quenched.
告诉我斯巴达克斯和那帮杂碎在哪儿
Tell me where Spartacus and his shits are to be found.
你所坚持的东西 他们根本不屑一顾
They have spat on everything you've held true.
你完全没必要袒护他们
You owe them nothing.
说话啊 该死的混蛋
Speak, you fucking cunt!
很好
Very well.
你就沉默吧
Remain silent.
半死不活地受苦吧
Remain living, and in pain.
日复一日
Day after day.
只有阿舒尔来慰劳你
With only Ashur to comfort you.
正如你曾在这沙场之上慰劳我
As you once comforted me upon these very sands.
他们来的事情 你应该告诉我
You should have warned me of their arrival.
我当时没想到嘛
I was swept by the moment.
他们只在那里站了一会儿
They stood but a short length waiting.
足够让你父亲给我脖子套个活结了
Long enough for your father to slip noose about my neck.
只要你率军表演 这些都无关紧要
All will be forgotten when you present your men.
那是为了看我的笑话
Oh to honor a jest of a man.
退下
Go.
是为了你的孩子
To honor your child.
他的父亲即将在元老院平步青云
With a father that will rise within the senate.
我不在乎瓦里留斯摸过你
I did not care for Varinius' hand upon you.
我也是
Nor I.
但他的抚摸绝不会让我这儿如此湿润
Yet his touch will never know wetter climes…
- 我没心思 还有工作要做 - 工作
- Pressing concerns pull mind from task. - Task?
你知道我什么意思
You know my meaning.
要和马科斯协商
Must confer with Marcus,
从南边召回我的军队
towards the recall of my troops from the south.
我们不能自相残杀
We must not fall to quarrel.
维苏威非常适合我们
Vesuvius will serve purpose well.
艾力冈建议到那不勒斯离河岸不远的地方
Agron speaks of fighting men to be liberated from Neapolis
解放被俘的战士
not far from it's banks.
艾力冈只配喝我的尿
Agron can suck the piss from my cock!
你那玩意儿太小 不够喝
Too small a drink for a man.
操你妈的
Fuck you!
- 维苏威有它的优势 - 该死的懦夫
- Vesuvius offers advantage. - Fucking coward!
我们能从后方攻击那不勒斯港口的船只
From its shadow we can strike the ports of Neapolis'…
救出罗马人抓来关在船上的战士
ships heavy with warriors captured by the Romans,
就跟我们以前一样
as many of us once were
我们听听克雷斯的意见
Let us hear from Crixus!
他能怎么说呢
And what would he say?
说了又有什么用呢
What words would make difference?
那些自言自语
The ones I have told myself?
那些希望
Ones of hope,
还有美好生活的承诺
and promise of better days?
我再也喊不出空洞的口号了
Throat can no longer make such empty noise.
嗓子堵住了
It is choked with loss.
我们很多人都有相似的痛苦
An agony familiar to many of us.
斯巴达克斯痛失爱妻
Spartacus lost his wife.
但他心里的火还在烧
Yet his fire still burns.
艾力冈 痛失手足
Agron, a brother.
但他心里的火没有灭
Yet his fire still burns.
我们都失去过
We have all lost.
我们都目睹过心爱的朋友
We have all seen those held as friend,
家人
as family,
爱人
as lover,
死于罗马人之手
fall to the Romans.
但我们心中的火仍在燃烧
Yet our fire still burns.
我们携手同心 就能燃起地狱之火
And together we shall ignite an inferno.
我和斯巴达克斯一起去维苏威
I move to Vesuvius with Spartacus.
你会开口的
You will speak.
在你弥留之际
In your final moments.
等你苦求我赐你一死
When you beg for life's end.
你会告诉我斯巴达克斯和…
You will tell me where Spartacus and
你个贱货
You fucking cunt!
我要打到你这张臭嘴说话
I shall tear the words from your fucking mouth!
阿舒尔
Ashur.
在预言实现之前 奥诺玛默斯不能死
Oenomaus must not die before prophecy is fulfilled.
那就祈求上天撬开他的嘴巴
Then entreat the fucking heavens to pry his lips.
或者管好你的嘴巴 免得自身不保
Or you would do well to seal your own, lest tongue escape you.
我真不该回到这里
I should never have returned to this house.
最终没什么好结果
Fortunes darken as consequence.
诸神自会给你光明
Look to the gods for illumination.
诸神
The gods?
是朱庇特在你奄奄一息时发现了你吗
Was it Jupiter, that found you near death?
是维纳斯把你的破肚子缝好了吗
Or Venus, who stitched your mangled womb?
是战神给你吃给你穿吗
Did Mars see you fed and clothed?
还是阿波罗把奥诺玛默斯交到你手中 不是
Did Apollo deliver Oenomaus into your hands? No.
是阿舒尔
It was Ashur!
最低贱的凡人
Lowest of fucking mortals!
你不过是奉诸神的意志行事
You but service the will of the gods.
我是为你做事
I was serving you.
而我为他们做事
And I them.
那恐怕我们都被抛弃了
Then I fear that we are both forsaken.
他不肯开口说话
The man will not speak.
只要他不开口 你的预言就没戏可唱了
Absent his words, your prophecy will fall to ruin.
你那些信徒也将离去
The pious quickly to follow.
即便是死人也有软肋
Even the dead may give voice to passion.
那家伙现在就是一具躯壳
The man stands empty of such worldly vice.
那就给他血肉
Then see him filled.
让他回忆过去
With memories of the past.
有一个深埋于高墙之内的秘密
There is a secret, buried within these walls.
你要将其挖掘出来
And you will see it exhumed,
就是死尸也会开口
and the corpse set to purpose…
时辰不早了
The hour grows late.
我们去暖床吧
And our bed cold.
去睡吧
Fall to it.
我等会儿就去陪你
I'll be with you presently.
最折磨人的 就是无止境地等待
The maddening thing, to forever be waiting for you.
离你那么远
Far from your side.
我身边并不安全
It's not always the safest place.
很多人都有亲身体验
As many have learned.
我跟她们不同
I am not the past.
我正站在你面前
I stand with you now.
我不仅可以抚慰你 满足你的需要
And would hold more value than gentle touch and satisfying your needs.
我还会站在你身边
I would stand beside you,
手执利刃 沾满罗马人的鲜血
blade gripped in hand slick with Roman blood.
我可以助你一臂之力 而不像妮维雅
I will not be helpless, as Naevia was.
她只能慢慢走向死亡
Her life slow march towards death.
我们都会有这一天
We all move towards such end.
只是时间长短不同
Only the length of the journey differs.
那我们就共赴此约吧
Then let us greet it together.
死也要轰轰烈烈
And show not all go quietly.
你打算把整座宅子都装进箱子吗
You intend to spirit away the entire villa in that trunk?
谁知道维苏威那儿有什么呢 夏达娜
We do not know what Vesuvius holds, Chadara.
艾力冈可以帮我们做好补给
Agron would have us well supplied.
是啊 艾力冈
Agron, yes.
他很有型 是吧
He is of a form, is he not?
算是吧
I suppose.
什么叫算是吧
Oh, you suppose?
别以为我没注意你看他的眼神
Do not think I have not noticed your eyes upon him.
更不用说后来你们凑在一起
Nor the way of late you have been huddled together
窃窃私语
in intimate conversation.
你完全想错了
You mistake subject of discussion.
他一靠近你的脸就红 这我可错不了
Yet not the blush upon your cheek when he is near.
你要好好打扮才能博得他的欢心
You would do yourself well to pursue desire.
他要是对我有意思 我就会这么做
I would myself, if I believed he favored me.
你不是看上莱斯克斯了吗
I thought you were taken with Rhaskos?
莱斯克斯就是禽兽
Rhaskos is a base animal.
不过他挺能打
Yet one with sharp claws,
可以保护我 给我地位
offering protection and position.
斯巴达克斯很看重艾力冈
Spartacus holds Agron in much high esteem.
我真羡慕你跟他那么好
I envy you his attentions.
如果我们借助运奴车
We can reach Vesuvius by nightfall,
日落前就能到维苏威了
if we put the slaver wagon to use.
走大路的危险难以预料
It would commit us to the roads.
丛林可以给我们打掩护
The forest will better hide our numbers.
但走得很慢
And slow progress.
无所谓 至少我们能安全到达山区
A fair trade, to see us all to the mountain alive.
克雷斯
Crixus.
你训练的时候我没说好话
I was not in favor of your training.
知道为什么吗
Do you know the reason?
因为我刺杀过斯巴达克斯
I made attempt on Spartacus.
这事儿我也干过 好多次呢
As have I, on more than one occasion.
因为我不相信你
I did not trust you.
因为你是叙利亚人
Because you are Syrian.
而我曾经与一个叙利亚人交恶
I have had unfortunate acquaintance with one of your people.
我的女人妮维雅也是
As did my woman, Naevia.
对不起
Apologies.
他给她带来了很多痛苦
He caused her much pain.
尽管如此
Yet despite this,
她也不会因为那人的行为对你心存芥蒂
she would not have held you for his actions.
她本性善良
Such was her heart.
这是我应该学习她的一点
One I shall try to honor, in thought and deed.
有件事我必须告诉你
There is something I must tell you…
罗马人当我们是惹人嫌的苍蝇
Rome considers us nagging fly.
等去了那不勒斯 他们就明白…
After Neapolis, they shall know the sting
艾力冈
Agron!
管好你的人
Take your man!
你他妈的混蛋
Fucking shit!
我要杀了你
I'll fucking kill you!
你疯了吗
Have you lost mind?
是复活了
Regained heart.
妮维雅还活着
Naevia lives.
你从哪儿听来的消息
How do you come by this?
是纳西尔
The boy Nasir.
那奴隶贩子没说妮维雅已死
The slaver told not of Naevia's death,
说的是她在矿区受苦受难
but of her suffering in the mines.
命该如此
An equal fate
你明明不知道她的死活
Why would you bear false tongue,
为什么要说谎
when a life holds in the balance?
那我们的死活呢
What of our lives?
谁管我们的死活
克雷斯满脑子想的都是妮维雅
Crixus has no thought towards any but Naevia.
要是他愚蠢地攻打矿区
And would have us all meet our end
我们全都得送命
in foolish attempt on the mines.
我只能这么做 斯巴达克斯
I did what needed to be done, Spartacus.
你要搞清楚
You must see this.
撒谎
A lie
是为了大家好
for the greater good.
要是你弟弟杜罗命悬一线
One that would never have passed lips,
你绝不会撒这个谎
had it been your brother Duro in her place.
要是一条人命可以牺牲
If a single life holds no value,
我们的命又有什么价值
then none are of worth.
我站在克雷斯这边
I stand with Crixus.
一定要救出妮维雅
And will see Naevia from bondage.
我才不要为这事儿送命
I will not fucking die for this!
我要去维苏威
I move for Vesuvius.
想活命的
Those that would live,
跟我走
join me.
他活过来了
He returns to us.
我在寒风的拥抱中 昼夜不眠地守着你
I have set vigil, throughout chill embrace of night.
多么担心我一怒之下
Concerned that in eruption I had ah
送你上了西天
released you to the afterlife.
看到你没离开这个世界 我满心欢喜
It swells heart, to find you yet bound to this world.
还是一言不发
Still not a word?
好吧 不说就不说
Very well. Save voice.
那就轮到我一吐为快了
I would enjoy the sweet caress of my own.
要说的太多了
So very much to speak of.
这座宅子多年的秘密
Long years of secrets within this house,
渗进了每一根房梁
seeping in the very bones that support it.
耳朵贴在横木上
Place ear to any beam,
那些低语声绝对吓你一跳
and marvel at the whispers of the past.
就在那里 我初见克雷斯
It was there that I first discovered Crixus,
抱着年轻的妮维雅 坠入悲情的爱河
embraced in ill fated love with the young Naevia.
在那里 主人答应提高我的地位
There, dominus blessed me with elevation,
只要干掉行政官克拉维斯
upon heel of ending Magistrate Calavius
然后栽赃给索罗尼斯
and cursing Solonius with the deed.
更深的地方
Further inside…
甘尼克斯染指了你的爱妻
where Gannicus first took your wife,
只为取悦尊贵的瓦鲁斯
as entertainment for noble Varus.
说谎
Lies.
顽石点头了
Stone at last cracks!
只为了帮那个婊子说话
In defense of a fucking whore.
你没那么蠢吧
Were you really so blind?
他们对视时缠绵的目光
The lingering gazes they shared?
你那位兄弟微妙的变化
The subtle change in your brother?
你
You
不配提起兄弟二字
know nothing of brotherhood…
甘尼克斯也不配
Nor did Gannicus.
你就没有扪心自问过
Have you never asked yourself how your wife
巴蒂塔斯准备的毒酒
came to sip a tainted wine
你老婆是如何尝到的
that was meant for Batiatus?
她没有小偷小摸的习惯 对吧
And she was not in habit of thieving, was she?
也不会独自喝酒
Or partaking of drink alone?
还记得那晚吗
Do you recall that night?
甘尼克斯第二天要被转手
Gannicus, to be sold the next morning.
你跟主人去了城镇
You, conveniently removed to town.
你的爱妻溜进甘尼克斯的房间
Your wife, slipping away into Gannicus' cell.
最后一杯酒
One last drink.
最后
One…
一次
last…
上床
fuck.
你们的命运如此相似
You're all the same.
斯巴达克斯 克雷斯
Spartacus. Crixus.
高贵的奥诺玛默斯
The noble Oenomaus.
因为别人享用了心爱的女人
Falling to ruin for women plowed
把自己折磨得生不如死
by other men's cock.
好好想想我说的话是不是真的
Search heart, and feel the sting of truth.
本是送给泰塔斯的酒
lt was a gift for Titus.
她怎么可能品尝到
How did it come to pass her lips?
她不会小偷小摸
She was no thief.
你的爱妻劈腿
Your wife betrayed you.
搞了你兄弟
Your brother.
你以为他们爱你 其实都背叛了你
Everyone you believed to love you.
狡猾的毒蛇怎能理解真爱
What does a serpent know of love?
爱情正如毒蛇 相当致命
That its bite is often fatal.
你的爱妻倒在了它的毒液中
Your wife fell to its venom.
叛徒斯巴达克斯的婊子也是
As did the traitor Spartacus' bitch.
即使趾高气昂的高卢人
Even the mighty Gaul saw his heart wither,
当妮维雅离开他的怀抱 也是撕心裂肺
when ripe Naevia was plucked forever from his grasp.
他们会找到她的
They will find her.
总有一天割开你的喉咙
And one day your fucking throat.
找到她
Find her?
因此他们才往南走
That is why they have moved south…
斯巴达克斯不是他们唯一的领头人
Spartacus is not the one that spurs their intent…
克雷斯
Crixus?
那个当着你和巴蒂塔斯的面
The Gaul who lost mind before you and Batiatus
企图攻击我的丧心病狂的高卢人
attacked me in his purpose then as now.
他喜欢主人的贴身奴隶 妮维雅
Love for Domina's body slave, Naevia.
你承诺找到斯巴达克斯的行踪
You pledge to discover Spartacus' location.
现在只有这般胡言乱语
Instead you return with tales of fluttering hearts?
她被献给了别人
She was taken from this house.
我了解克雷斯 他不会善罢甘休
I know Crixus, he will not rest until
给他上刑
See him to proper reward.
且慢
Wait! Wait! Wait!
你真要背离神明
You would turn from the gods,
拒绝神的指引
and their guidance?
即使这条狗吐出的是真话
Even if this crude vessel disgorged truth,
他提供的线索无非就是
such knowledge provides little more
微风拂过鸿毛
than feather upon breeze.
而我知道何处平静无风
Yet I know of calming winds…
渺小黑暗的羽毛
and where dark little feather came
雨过天晴后的安息之地
to rest at tempest's end.
别死了 你这大傻蛋
Do not die, you simple fuck.
我死了你会为我哀悼吗
Will you mourn me if I do?
会 直到遇上更能满足我的男人
Until I find better to fill me.
婊子
Bitch.
我们是裸体上战场 拿老屌当武器吗
Are we to attack naked, with our cocks as weapon?
无妨 反正你能行
You would fare just as well.
赶紧从我眼前消失
Remove yourself from fucking sight.
走吧
Go.
去维苏威找我们
Seek us out at Vesuvius.
如果你们还活着
If you live.
你最好祈祷我死了
Pray I do not.
我跟主人去过矿区
I accompanied my dominus to the mines once.
或许能帮上忙
I may be of some aid.
热烈欢迎
Well received.
操蛋的叙利亚人
Fucking Syrians.
马车备好了
The wagon is readied.
斯巴达克斯
Spartacus…
留着对妮维雅说吧
Save words for Naevia.
在她重新投入你怀抱之时
When we have returned her to your arms.
但愿如此
I would have it so.
或者当场战死
Or perish in the attempt.
狗杂种们 快干活
Move along you fucking dogs!
不要暴露烙印
Do not expose brand.
当我们是普通奴隶 我们才有戏可唱
We would lose advantage of being thought as common slaves.
让李斯卡斯脑袋开花更容易搪塞过去
A crack to Liscus' skull would add to the deception.
小声点
Lower voice.
别停下 杂种们
Keep moving cunt.
别指望坐在车上我会给你们钱
Do I give coin to sit upon ass?
让他们全都滚下来
See them from the fucking wagon.
下去
Out!
动作快点
Hurry up!
这是菲若克斯的货吗
Is this the stock from Ferox?
比预期迟了两天时间
Two days past expected delivery.
他妈的整整两天
Two fucking days!
- 抱歉… - 我不认识你
- Apologies, I - I do not know you.
菲若克斯人呢
Where is Ferox?
死了
Dead.
我们遭到了斯巴达克斯那帮混蛋的袭击
We were set upon by Spartacus and his shits.
所以才迟到 菲若克斯也来不成了
The reason for our delay and Ferox's permanent absence.
我早就盼着那家伙死翘翘了
I have wished the man to grass for many years.
可他死了也不放过我
Yet he fucks me from the afterlife.
时间耽搁了这么久
Schedule now teeters upon brink,
我的损失没办法弥补了
with little hope of regaining balance.
再次向您道歉…
Yes, again, apologies
该介绍我了吧
Am I to present myself now?
是的
Yes. Yes!
这是附赠给您的 用来补偿您的损失
A special offering, to compensate your troubles…?
站好
Wait here.
别拿烂逼糊弄我
Rotten cunt serves no trade.
这么漂亮 犯了什么罪送到矿上来
What misdeed sees such beauty condemned to the mines?
说话 别等我的老二堵住你喉咙
Form words, or find my cock reason you cannot.
我恋爱了
I fell in love.
在这儿你就放心吧
No danger of that here…
现在轮到你说话了
I would have you form words now.
否则我割了你的老二
Or find your cock upon the floor.
巴蒂塔斯家有个女人被送到这里了
There was a woman brought here from the House of Batiatus.
年轻漂亮
Beautiful and young.
像你这种死胖子肯定注意到了
One a fat shit like you would have taken notice of.
说
Speak.
没见过你说的这号人
I know of no such woman.
给老娘好好想想
Search fucking memory.
深色皮肤
She is dark of skin.
肩膀后面有巴蒂塔斯老婆的标记
With the mark of Batiatus' wife upon the back of her shoulder.
我想起来了 有一个跟你说的很像
I do recall one as you just described.
她还没死吧
Does she yet draw breath?
我想是的
I believe it so.
她在哪儿
Where is she?
派去挖东边的矿脉了
Assigned to dig the eastern vein.
这里有地图
There is a map…
指给我看
Show me.
慢点儿
Slowly.
米拉去了太久
Mira is gone too long.
那边的
You there.
你从哪儿来
From where do you hail?
西西里
Sicilia.
在这边的岔道里 这儿…
In the tunnel that branches off. Here
我以前见过你
I have seen you before…
在什么地方
somewhere…
竞技场…
The arena
钥匙 快
Keys. Quickly.
米拉
Mira!
是罗马人的血
It is Roman blood.
那人知道她吗
Did he know of her?
妮维雅活着吗
Does Naevia live?
活着
She does.
曼努斯 普莱努斯
Mannus. Plenus.
换上他们的衣服
Assume their mantle.
一旦有人发现就立刻报信
Make it known if any become aware of our presence.
进矿坑 快
Into the mines. Quickly.
走吧 兄弟
Come brother.
我们去了却心愿
Let us see heart restored.
走
Go…
走 走
Move. Go!
你该尝尝这个
Hm, You really must try this.
太美味了
It's divine.
我这时候有点反胃
I fear stomach turned at the moment.
我可不嫉妒你
I do not envy you.
每天日出都要呕吐
Sickness with every sunrise.
无缘无故地发胖
Swelling beyond reason.
不过对胸部蛮有好处的
Though the breasts are a benefit, I suppose.
感受胎儿在腹中成长…
To feel a child grow within you…
这是最幸福的事了
There is no greater blessing.
不做妇女就不幸福吗
What of being sort of other than matron?
拿青春美貌引诱男人 听他们百般奉承
Enticing men until they fawn over your every word,
就为了摸摸你 这样不幸福吗
aching to receive the slightest touch?
这是维系婚姻所必要的结果
The bonds of marriage desired result.
没有这么可怕吧
I suppose it would not be too horrid.
只要他英俊而又富有
If he were handsome. And rich.
整天只想着抚摸我 这就行了
And thought of nothing but his hands upon me.
欲望之类的东西
Lust, as all things,
全都随着时间而消退
fades with the passing of years.
太阳升高了
Sun draws high.
我们就座吧 开始今日比赛
Let us fall to our seats, and see day begin.
瓦里留斯说你的手下要登台表演
Varinius tells that your men are to be presented.
是
Yes.
如果你的手下是正规军
The request would have fallen to yours,
任务就落到你头上了
if they were proper soldiers.
那我就等着见识罗马正规军的风采了
I look forward to witnessing proper Roman formation.
市民的情绪也能振作起来
It should be a pleasant distraction for the people…
同时我的手下去捉拿斯巴达克斯
while my men bring Spartacus to justice.
没错
Yes.
你的士兵都安排就位了吧
Your soldiers are to purpose?
是的
They are.
你来发言 瓦里留斯
The crowd is yours, Varinius.
卡普亚的各位市民
Good citizens of Capua!
我用这场比赛向罗马的好姐妹致敬
I present these games to honor the beloved sister of Rome!
并且传达这样一个信息
And to send message that her spirit
她的精神永远不灭
shall never be quelled
企图伤害她的暴徒无法得逞
by those that seek to cause her injury.
你们往后的欢呼喝彩
Your cheers in the coming days
犹如良药 定能抚慰伤痛的心
shall serve as balm to wounded heart.
这座伟大城市的子民所共同承受的伤痛
A wound shared by many in this great city,
罪魁祸首则是斯巴达克斯及其杀人团伙
so inflicted by the treachery of Spartacus
令人发指的叛逆行为
and his murderous horde.
我在此号召罗马之子整装前行
I call now upon the sons of Rome to march,
步步惊雷 是为宣言
the thunder of their every step a declaration!
死亡与哀痛
That loss and grief
终将化为凯旋的狂欢
shall give way to triumph and joy!
你的手下躲哪儿去了
Where are your fucking men?
安排就位了 我说到做到
Set to purpose, as promised.
守住道路
Seal the road.
你
You!
我们奉民政官葛雷博之命前来
We come on order of Praetor Gaius Claudius Glaber.
有没有人企图破坏矿区
Has attempt been made to breach the mines?
没有 安然无事
None. It stands secure.
送话去卡普亚
Dispatch word to Capua.
此行徒劳无获
I would turn from fool's errand
我请求再去郊区搜查
and recommit to sweep the countryside
抓住他
Seize him!
我认得这些人
I know these men!
曼努斯和普莱努斯 角斗士
Mannus and Plenus! Gladiators,
身上有巴蒂塔斯家族的烙印
bearing the mark of Batiatus!
斯巴达克斯就在这里
Spartacus is here.
该走哪条路
Which way do we go?
两条路都能找到她
They both should lead us to her.
这条路近一点
This one the shorter path.
越是接近越不可轻率
I would double odds toward goal.
走远路 动作轻点
Take the longer path. Move quietly.
卡普亚的人民
People of Capua!
尊贵的瓦里留斯
Noble Varinius!
我向你们致歉
I offer apologies!
士兵们并未前来列阵
I do not seek to lower spirits
不是要挫败斗志
with absence of display,
反而是鼓舞精神
but instead to raise them up!
因为我的士兵们
With knowledge that my soldiers
受到诸神的指引
have been set to higher purpose
前去追寻更崇高的目标
by the gods themselves!
此时此刻 他们已逼近斯巴达克斯
At this very moment, they close on Spartacus!
日落之前 他将再次跪倒在
And by day's end, he shall once more kneel
罗马的荣光之下
before the glory of Rome!
罗马
Rome!
罗马 罗马
Rome! Rome!
我们要给他们自由
We must see them freed.
人数太多了
There are too many of them.
会被察觉的
We would be discovered.
活下去
Live.
有朝一日我会回来的
And know I will return.
妮维雅
Naevia?
Naevia!
这是他说的地方吗
This is where he said she would be?
如果所言属实的话
If he spoke truth.
克雷斯
Crixus!
这有个人 肩膀后有主人家的标记
There is one here, with mark of her domina upon back!
妮维雅
Naevia…?
Naevia?
不
No…
你没事了
You are safe…
现在安全了
You are safe, now.
我在这里
I'm here…
I'm here.
克雷斯
Crixus?
原谅我
Forgive me…
原谅我所做的一切
Forgive me for what I have done.
斯巴达克斯 有人来了
Spartacus! Someone comes
撤 快撤
Go! Go!
阿舒尔
Ashur!
走 快走啊
Move! Move!
快走
Go!
在这里
Here!
且慢
Wait!
有条地下河
There's a runoff.
通向矿区的另一端
It empties out on the other side of the mine.
该走哪条路
Which path do we take?
快
Quickly!
这边
This way.
她这是把我们往死路上引
She leads us to our fucking death!
深呼吸 找到方向感
Take breath, and gain your bearing.
少转了一道弯
A turn missed.
那里通向水流所在
It will take us to the water.
在这里
Here!
快走
Move!
等等
Wait!
快点 走
Come on! Go!
我来拖住他们
I will give them pause,
这样你就能逃出去了
so you may slip from grasp.
你们两个下去
You two down there!
保证妮维雅的安全
See Naevia to safety.
克雷斯
Crixus!
交给你了 兄弟
See it done, brother.
快走
Go!
斯巴达克斯
Spartacus!
走吧
Go!
操你妈
Fuck you!
你们这帮畜生
Fuck you bastards!
杀 杀 杀
Kill, kill, kill…
克雷斯
Crixus!